Guide to the Time Inc. Time Publishing and Business Records 1929-1999 MS 3009-RG 24
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Office of the Business Manager Files, 1929-1977; 12.25 Linear feet in 13 record cartons
  - Subseries II.F. General Administrative Files, 1929-1975; 191570; 4.5 Linear feet in 5 record cartons
    - Management of Editorial Services, 1958; 191610 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 32)
    - Metallic Ink, 1939, 1946-1948 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 33)
    - Morgue, 1944-1957 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 34)
    - Newsweek, 1946-1965; 191611 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 1-5)
    - News Bureau, 1944-1958; 191612 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 6-9)
    - Office Management, 1953-1957; 191615 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 10)
    - Office Space, 1957; 191616 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 11)
    - Operating Statement Analyses, 1946-1947; 191617 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 12)
    - Ownership Statements (PS Form 3526), 1929-1975; 191618 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 13-19)
    - Personnel: Employee Relations, 1952; 191619 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 20)
    - Personnel: Jochanan, Scott [RESTRICTED UNTIL 2033], 1958; 191620 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Personnel Reports, 1942-1958; 191621 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 21-25)
    - PIB [Publishers Information Bureau], 1956; 191623 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 26)
    - Production, 1946-1952; 193195 (Offsite-box 3132, Folder 27-29)
    - Profit Trends, 1948-1959; 191625 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 1-3)
    - Special Luce Project, 1958-1959; 193197 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 4)
    - Speeches, 1943-1948, 1956, undated; 191626 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 6-7)
    - Sports Illustrated [empty], undated; 191627 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 8)
    - Staff Memoranda, 1957; 191628 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 9)
    - Staff, Payroll and Raises Report, 1955; 191629 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 10)
    - Standard Cost, 1946-1949; 191630 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 11-12)
    - Steering Committee, 1957; 191631 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 13)
    - Studies, 1949; 191633 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 14)
    - Studies: Extra Text Pages, 1953 (Offsite-box 3113, Folder 15)
    - Studies: River Club Meeting, 1954; 191634 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 16)
    - Surveys, 1950-1951; 191635 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 17)
    - Taxes, 1950; 191636 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 18)
    - Tearsheets, 1954-1955; 191637 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 19)
    - Time: Division Updates, 1964-1966; 193199 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 20)
    - Time: Final Budget, 1947; 193200 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 21)
    - Time: MAC Speeches, 1945 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 22)
    - Time: Profit Loss Statements, 1945-1955; 193201 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 23-25)
    - Time Inc. Policies, 1938, 1947, 1954-1958; 191638 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 26)
    - TLI [Time Life International] [empty], undated; 191639 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 27)
    - Travel Bureau, 1956-1960; 191640 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 28-29)
    - Tycoon Typing Company, 1955; 191641 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 30)
    - UP-AP [empty], undated; 191643 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 31)
    - Vacation Policy, 1958; 191644 (Offsite-box 3133, Folder 32)
  - Subseries II.G. Personnel Files, 1941-1963; 2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
    Personnel Files contain the personnel records maintained by the Office of the Business Manager and include personnel cards for individual staff and files on personnel issues such as policies and salaries. The majority of restricted folders are restricted because of personally identifiable information or performance reviews.
    - General, 1958-1962 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 1)
    - Administration [RESTRICTED], 1962 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Advertising Promotion [RESTRICTED], 1962-1964 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Advertising Sales [RESTRICTED], 1962-1964 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Editorial Copy Desk [RESTRICTED], 1962 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Editorial Photon and Teletypesetters [RESTRICTED], 1962-1963 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Editorial Pictures and Production, 1962-1964 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 2)
    - Editorial Researchers [RESTRICTED], 1962-1965 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Editorial Secretaries [RESTRICTED], 1962-1963 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Editorial Writers, 1962-1964 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 3)
    - Headcount Reconciliation, 1961-1964 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 4-7)
    - Job Descriptions, 1962 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 8)
    - Leave of Absences [RESTRICTED], 1962 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Letters Department [RESTRICTED], 1962-1964 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Loan Requests [RESTRICTED], 1962 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Marketing Services [RESTRICTED], 1962-1963 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Newspaper Build of New York, 1945-1962 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 9-11)
    - Policy, 1948-1954 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 12)
    - Raise Review, 1960-1963 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 13-17)
    - Salary: General Increase, 1952-1956 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 18-21)
    - Salary: Mandatory Increase, 1961-1963 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 22-23)
    - Salary Review, 1949-1954 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 24)
    - Staff Cards [RESTRICTED], 1941-1963 (Offsite-box 3134)
      Staff cards include dates of hire and departure along with salary information. They are grouped chronologically by the year the staff member left Time.
    - Targets, 1953, 1958 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 25-26)
    - Teletypesetters, 1949 (Offsite-box 3135, Folder 27)
- Series III. Advertising Promotion Department Records, 1936-1969; 6.2 Linear feet in 6 record cartons, 1 flat box
  The Advertising Promotion Department promoted the magazine to appeal to advertisers, although this department is separate from the Advertising Sales Department.
  The Advertising Promotion Department Records contain files from Promotion Director Robert Fisler, Executive Promotion Director Dave Aubrey, Promotion Director Richard Coffey, and assistant to the director Alan Martin. The records document this department's efforts to attract advertisers, market testing, and presentations to the advertising sales staff.
  To see a list of advertising campaigns in Time magazine from 1923 to 1971, see the Time Advertising Promotion series in Time Inc. Index Cards (MS 3009-RG 4).
  Organized into two subseries:
  Subseries III.A. Promotion Director Robert Fisler Files
  Subseries III.B. Promotion Director: General Files
  - Subseries III.A. Promotion Director Robert Fisler Files, 1936-1968; 5 Linear feet in 5 record cartons
    According to his files and the department head lists, Robert "Bob" Fisler was in the Corporate Circulation Department as an assistant to Time Promotion Writer William Baring-Gould prior to 1950. From 1950 to 1955 he was in Time Circulation as the Promotion Manager. From 1956 to 1961 he was in Time Advertising Promotion as the Promotion Manager, the top role in the department. By 1962, his title had changed to Promotion Director while still remaining the top role. One of his duties was writing the copy in the circulation promotion mailings.
    A letter in his 1959 Personal folder refers to him as the Sports Illustrated Promotion Director, and his records contain some Sports Illustrated materials. He may have briefly done side work for at this publication. In 1966 he moved to Life Promotion as the Promotion Director.
    Fisler's files span the period he was employed at Time through his transition to Life. The majority of his office files are from Time. Although there are records from both of his roles the Circulation Department and the Advertising Promotion Department, his files were not separated as such, and this series is listed under his later position with Advertising Promotion.
    Originally his files were loosely separated into a mixture of office files from Time and Life, speech files, personal files which contain both personal and business correspondence, and material from his aunt's company St. John Associates Inc.
    Organized into three subsubseries:
    Subsubseries II.A.1. Office Files
    Subsubseries II.A.2. Personal Files
    Subsubseries II.A.3. Speech Files
    - Subsubseries III.A.1. Office Files, 1952-1968; 1.5 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
      Office Files include copy for the promotion mailings; notes on his own speeches and speeches collected by Fisler; responses to Fisler sending out books from the Time Reading Program; planning for a business trip to Japan for advertising market research; some records from his predecessor Advertising Promotion Director Nick Samstag, possibly inherited; and work assigned to him by Time Publisher Bernard Auer to assist Williams College with their alumni fund. Additional Williams College material is in the Personal Files. Some materials on Life date from before he transferred roles.
      - American Alumni Council, 1962 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 1)
      - Asia Newstour (Southeast Asia?) Binder, 1965 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 2-3)
      - Aspen Insitute for Humanistic Studies: Executive Program, 1963 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 4-5)
      - Congratulatory Messages, 1952-1955 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 6)
      - Ivy Alumni Network: Analysis of 1965 Mail Response, 1966 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 7)
      - Ivy League Schools: "Ivied Tower of Babel", 1965 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 8)
      - Japan Trip, 1965 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 9-10)
      - Life Ideas, 1960-1968 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 11-13)
      - Life Space Tours, 1964-1966 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 14-15)
        The Life Space Tour was similar to the Time newstours of the United States, but were specific to space installations such as NASA and the U.S. Air Force bases. Guests included executives of America's leading consumer goods corporations. The purpose was to give the executives a complete understanding of why the space program is so complex, expensive, and rewarding to the country.
      - Life Sales Convention, 1967 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 16)
      - New York State Citizens Committee for Public Schools, 1955-1956 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 17)
      - Philosophical Memoranda, 1961-1965 (Offsite-box 3126, Folder 18-19)
      - "Pursuit of Excellence" Theme, 1959 (Offsite-box 3127, Folder 1)
      - Time 1960 Review, 1959-1961 (Offsite-box 3127, Folder 2-3)
      - Time Strategic Advertising Box Set, 1962 (Offsite-box 3127, Folder 4)
      - 2000 Word Memoranda, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 3127, Folder 5-6)
        This was an invitation to everyone in the department to send in a 2000 word memo on the subject of "What is TIME's most important promotion selling need at the moment?"
      - Williams College, 1964-1965 (Offsite-box 3127, Folder 7-8)
    - Subsubseries III.A.2. Personal Files, 1936-1966; 2.5 Linear feet in 3 record cartons
      Personal Files include folders titled "Personal" which are a mix of personal bills and correspondence and business correspondence and memoranda; files on Fisler's banking and club memberships; and files on St. John Associates Inc., a direct mail service in Manhattan owned by his aunt Helen V. Fisler. St. John Associates files include newsletters, ad cards, and client mass mailings which may be personal collecting on a family business or may be materials he used to assist him in his own job. It isn't clear if St. John Associates and Time Inc. had a business relationship in the 1950s and 1960s, but the Time Education Program used them as one of their mail services in the 1970s.
      Organized alphabetically with general files at the front.
      - General through '55, 1950-1957 (Offsite-box 3127, Folder 9)
      - General '55, 1953-1955 (Offsite-box 3127, Folder 10-11)
        Includes two dummies for Sports Illustrated from 1953 and 1954.
      - General '55 [RESTRICTED], 1955 (Offsite-box R26)
      - General '56, 1956 (Offsite-box 3127, Folder 12)
      - General '59, 1959 (Offsite-box 3127, Folder 13-14)
        Includes his telephone book listing contacts.
      - General '59, 1959 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 1)
      - General 1961 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 2)
      - General 1962 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 3)
      - General, 1962-1966 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 4-6)
        Includes portrait photographs of Fisler and photographs of him at work events.
      - Bonnie Briar Country Club, 1964-1965 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 7-8)
      - Hundred Million Club, 1954-1955 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 9)
      - Manufacturers Hanover Trust Company, 1965 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 10)
      - Royal National Bank of New York, 1936-1964 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 11)
        Includes account books from East River Savings Bank and Flatbush Federal Savings and Loan Association of Brooklyn.
      - Sleepy Hollow Country Club, 1964-1966 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 12-13)
      - St. John Associates Inc., 1946-1963 (Offsite-box 3128, Folder 14-17)
        The folders for 1958-1963 have extensive Williams College promotional material which may have been misfiled from the Williams College files.
      - St. John Associates Inc., 1958-1966 (Offsite-box 3129)
      - Taxes [RESTRICTED], 1952 (Offsite-box R26)
    - Subsubseries III.A.3. Speech Files, 1952-1965; 1 Linear feet in 1 record carton
      Speeches include copies of speeches given by Fisler along with collected copies of speeches given by others. Speeches were on the topics of sales, advertising, and marketing, and audiences included staff from various Time Inc. publications and attendees of national sales conventions, university events, and advertising clubs and associations. This subseries includes several speeches by Time Inc. president Roy Larsen.
      The 1955 file contains a speech by Advertising Promotion Director Nicholas Samstag on the topic of "Time's Greatest Promotion Asset."
      - Speeches, 1952-1965 (Offsite-box 3130)
  - Subseries III.B. Promotion Director: General Files, 1957, 1966-1969; 1.2 Linear feet in 1 record carton, 1 flat box
    Records are a mix of files from Advertising Promotion Executive Promotion Director Dave Aubrey, Promotion Director Richard Coffey, and assistant to the director Alan Martin.
    - Art Directors of Advertising Agencies Contest, 1968 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 1-5)
    - Editorial Presentation, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 6-9)
    - 45th Anniversary Presentation Research, 1967 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 10)
    - Ideas, 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 11)
    - Keep New York Cool, 1968 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 12)
    - Lincoln Center, 1967 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 13)
    - Lists: General, 1965-1967 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 14)
    - Lists: Past Promotion Pieces, 1969 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 15)
    - Lists: Meeting with Young & Rubicam, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 16)
    - Omnibus VI: Volume II: "The Staff of Life" Script, 1957 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 17)
    - Print Presentation, undated (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 18)
    - Sales Presentation, 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 19-20)
    - Sales Refresher Sessions, 1967 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 21)
    - Time Audio Edition Proposal and Market Testing, 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 22)
    - Time's Group Graffiti Contest: Invitation Booklet, 1967 (Offsite-box 1788)
    - Time-Life International Informal History, 1965 (Offsite-box 3013, Folder 23)
- Series IV. Promotion and Public Affairs Department Records, 1955-1999; 155.1 Linear feet in 156 record cartons, 1 document case, and 2 flat boxes
  Time Promotion and Public Affairs seems to be the most robust public affairs department after Corporate Public Affairs. It handled several events that promoted Time Inc. as a company as well as a magazine, such as: coordinating travel and accommodations for Time Inc. staff and corporate guests when Time Inc. was a sponsor of the Olympics; organizing major annual conferences and symposiums like the Housing Industry Presidents' Conference; and overseeing projects and initiatives such as the Distinguished Speakers Program and the Time-Life Academy of Transition.
  Up until 1967, there is no mention in the corporate structure of Time magazine of a public affairs department. Time did have a marketing department and an advertising promotion department since the earliest saved Department Heads List in the Time Inc. Reference Files.
  While Robert Sweeney is listed in the 1966 Department Heads List as an assistant to the Time publisher, he signs off as a member of Time Public Affairs in his 1966 files. It is possible public affairs was within the Publisher's Office even earlier, but not recorded as part of the structure.
  Beginning in 1967, Sweeney is officially listed as the Time public affairs director under Management along side of the publisher, general manager, and business manager. He continues to appear with this title through 1969. In 1969 the Advertising Promotion Department drops the word "Advertising" and becomes the Promotion Department.
  In 1970, Sweeney moves over to the newly established Corporate Public Affairs, and no one is listed as part of Time Public Affairs. No magazine lists its own public affairs department, and it is possible public affairs services were centralized.
  In 1972 public affairs reappears as Promotion/Public Affairs headed by director C. Lane Fortinberry who is also an assistant publisher, and Robert Ankerson as the director of public affairs. Former promotion staff are also part of this department.
  By 1974, the department is called General Promotion, still headed by assistant publisher Fortinberry and listing some of the same staff. The department now oversees special events and an art director. By 1978 Sweeney takes over as the director of General Promotion and holds this title until 1982. Also by 1978 General Promotion has added a publicity director.
  By August 1983 General Promotion and Public Affairs have split into separate offices. George Berger takes over as the director of General Promotion, and Sweeney is listed as the director of Public Affairs overseeing the public affairs manager, the publicity manager, and the special events manager. GP oversees the promotion manager, creative director, and art director.
  By 1985 Berger is replaced by Katherine Erskine and the position of creative director disappears.
  By the end of 1987, Promotion and Public Affairs are again one office with Daniel Brewster as Promotion & Public Affairs Director. The office oversees the business planning manager, art director, public affairs manager, promotion manager, and special events manager.
  The Time Promotion and Public Affairs document the organizing of special events and functions for both for Time Inc. and Time staff and events that included guests from outside of the company; organizing advertising competitions; photographs of internal and public events; and a decade of press releases. Special events include milestone anniversaries, exhibitions of art owned by the company, conferences, and newstours to other countries.
  This series is organized into 17 subseries:
  Subseries IV.A. Director Robert Sweeney Files
  Subseries IV.B. Public Affairs Manager Irina Bagration Files
  Subseries IV.C. Public Affairs Manager Anne Janas Files
  Subseries IV.D. Publicity Manager Files
  Subseries IV.E. Special Event Manager Jean C. Gussenhoven Files
  Subseries IV.F. Promotion Manager Nancy Hall Megan Files
  Subseries IV.G. Public Affairs Coordinator Jelmir Lucas Files
  Subseries IV.H. Advertising Campaign Files: "Make Time for Time"
  Subseries IV.I. Bio Files
  Subseries IV.J. Event Files
  Subseries IV.K. Newstour Files
  Subseries IV.L. Photographs and Negatives
  Subseries IV.M. Press Clippings, Kits, and Releases
  Subseries IV.N. Press Releases
  Subseries IV.O. Project Files
  Subseries IV.P. Promotion Realia
  Subseries IV.Q. General Office Files
  - Subseries IV.A. Director Robert Sweeney Files, 1955-1969, 1981; 8 Linear feet in 9 record cartons
    According to his files, Robert Sweeney worked on publicity for Fortune and Life from 1956 to 1962, then special projects for Life in 1963. According the the Department Head Lists for 1960 to 1961, he worked in Time Inc. Corporate as a publicity assistant. This role may have assisted all magazines. According to his obituary in the July 30, 1990 issue of the company newsletter FYI, Sweeney was appointed the creative projects director for Life in 1960.
    By 1964, Sweeney signs off as the Time director of public relations. In 1966, the Department Head List records him as an assistant to the Time Publisher. Time has no public affairs position at this time, and the role may have been handled by the publisher's office until Sweeney is listed under Time Management as the Public Affairs Director in 1967. He holds this job until 1970 when he moves to Corporate Public Affairs.
    According to VP of Corporate Public Affairs Donald Wilson's files, Sweeney returns to Time Public Affairs (now called General Promotion) in 1976 taking over as the director of General Promotion. His title changes to Worldwide Director of Public Affairs and Special Events in 1983. According to FYI, he retired in 1986. His obituary in FYI gives him credit for the creation of the newstour and proposing the bicentennial issue.
    Robert Sweeney's files include some from when he was a corporate publicity assistant covering all magazines, when he was creative project director for Life, when he was listed as an assistant to Time publisher, but primarily are from his role as director of Time Public Affairs. Because one group of his files sent to the archives spans various roles plus his position in Public Affairs, all of his files are kept together in this record group.
    Records include various publicity suggestions and the planning documents for various events and projects organized by or sponsored by Time Inc. magazines.
    Subsubseries III.A.1. Director Administrative Files
    Subsubseries III.A.2. Director Event Files
    Subsubseries III.A.3. Corporate Publicity, Life Special Projects, and Time Public Affairs Files
    - Subsubseries III.A.1. Director Administrative Files, 1967-1969, 1981; 3.5 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
      Files include some records from Stan Kapner, the associate director of public affairs; Putney Westerfield, a Time assistant publisher; Robert Krefting, later an assistant to the news service chief of correspondents, but here signs off as part of Public Affairs; and Ellen Stancs, who signs off as part of Public Affairs. Although some folders are completely records from these other individuals, the majority are Sweeney and Kapner, and it seems the files belong to Sweeney as director.
      Records include correspondence sent to Publisher James Shepley and President James Linen, probably forwarded for Public Affairs to handle; invitations to major news events such as the Apollo 8 launch; planning materials for community relations events organized or sponsored by Time such as the unofficial collegiate presidential primary vote called Choice 68; and arrangements for meetings between Time staff and prominent invidivuals.
      Organized in chronological groups by year and alphabetically within each year based on the original arrangement.
      - American Heritage Awards Banquet, 1968 (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 1)
      - Apollo 8, 1968 (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 2)
      - Automotive Warehouse Distributors 1968 Conference (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 3)
      - College Presidents' Conference, 1968 (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 4)
      - College Primary (Choice 68), 1968 (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 5-6)
      - Creativity Conference, 1968 (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 7)
      - Czech Managers Meeting and Training, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 8)
      - Demarest, Michael: Film, 1968 (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 9)
      - Doman-Delacato Theory Article and Response, 1968 (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 10)
      - Foreign Policy Association Tour, 1968 (Offsite-box 3051, Folder 11-22)
      - 40th Anniversary Dinner: Cover Subject Research, 1967 (Offsite-box 3052, Folder 1)
      - 45th Anniversary Dinner, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 3052, Folder 2-3)
      - Fuerbringer, Otto: Publisher's Dinner, 1968 (Offsite-box 3052, Folder 4)